Guide to the Robert B. Stevens Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert B. Stevens Papers
1961-1974
MS 1686
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
The papers consist of reports, correspondence, and working papers documenting the professional life of Robert Stevens and the activities of the E.A.C.S.O., the East African Community, and the Commission on East African Cooperation.
Stevens, Robert Bocking, 1933-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator, 1995.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. East African Common Services Organization, 1961-1966. II. Commission on East African Cooperation, 1966. III. East African Community, 1966-1974. IV. Subject Files, 1963-1973.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains reports, correspondence, and working papers documenting the professional life of Robert Stevens and the activities of the E.A.C.S.O., the East African Community, and the Commission on East African Cooperation.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Bocking Stevens was born in 1933. He received his legal education from Oxford University and Yale University, and then practiced law in New York and London. In 1959 he began teaching at the Yale University Law School, where he became a professor of law in 1964. He also taught law at Oxford, the London School of Economics, Northwestern, Stanford, the University of Texas, and the University of East Africa. Stevens specialized in commercial law, jurisprudence, and legal history. In the 1960s he served as a legal and constitutional advisor to the East African Common Services Organization (E.A.C.S.O.) And its successor, the East African Community. These organizations managed the East African Common Market and various joint economic services provided for member states. The founding members were Uganda, Kenya, and Tanganyika (later Tanzania). Stevens also advised the Commission on East African Cooperation (C.E.A.C.), which oversaw the transition between the E.A.C.S.O. and the East African Community.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Stevens, Robert Bocking, 1933-; Commission on East African Cooperation; East African Common Services Organization; East African Community; Yale Law School; Yale University -- Faculty
- East African Common Services Organization (E.A.C.S.O.), 1961-1966; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains papers related to the operations and policies of the East African Common Services Organization, and commentaries and opinions on that organization. It is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Commentaries on constitution [of E.A.C.S.O.], 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - East African Airways, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General report to Commission on East African Cooperation [on state of E.A.C.S.O.], 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Trade
    - Commentaries, 1963, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - East African Common Market economic data, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - East African Common Market treaty, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - East African Economic Community [proposal for], 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Kampala agreement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Trade report [international trade within East Africa], 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Treaty [establishment of EACSO], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - UNESCO resolutions, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Commission on East African Cooperation (C.E.A.C.), 1966; Series II
  The series contains papers documenting the operations, policies, and recommendations of the Commission on East African Cooperation. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject, except for the working papers of the Commission, which are arranged as originally written.
  - Commentary on East African Common Services Organization management, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Constitutional and legal problems [of East African Common Services Organization], 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Constitutional working party, 1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Final report of C.E.A.C., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Operations, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Policies, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Working papers
    - Contents, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Foreword, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Common Market, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - Common services
      - General, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Railways and habours, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Posts and telecommunications, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Aviation, civil aviation, and meteorology, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Higher education, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Research, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Taxation and finance, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Possible new services, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Relocation of headquarters, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Administrative questions, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Constitutional questions, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- East African Community, 1967-1974; Series III
  This series contains papers related to the East African Community, which superseded the East African Common Services Organization in 1967. It is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Commentary on East African Common Market, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - East African Negotiating Team
    - Operations, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Applications for admission [to East African Community]
      - Implications for applicant states, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - Burundi, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
      - Ethiopia, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Somalia, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Swaziland, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Zambia, 1967, 1969-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 11-14)
  - European Economic Community [agreement with], 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Treaty [establishment of East African Community], 1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1963-1973; Series IV
  The series is arranged alphabetically by subject, and contains papers documenting the professional life of Robert B. Stevens.
  - Biography, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Court cases, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - East African unity
    - Julius K. Nyerere speech [President of Tanganyika], 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Proposed federation, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Yale [legal history courses], 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)